Finding Aid for Michigan Civil Service Study Commission records, 1935-1941
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Michigan Civil Service Study Commission records 1935-1941
Michigan. Civil Service Study Commission.
851842 Ca.4b 2
Correspondence, reports, minutes, financial records, drafts of bills and clippings, including the 1936 report of the Public Administration Service on existing conditions in Michigan.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
6 linear feet
The record group was the gift of Professor James K. Pollock (donor no. 1048 ) and came to the library in 1941.
Periodic additions to the records are not expected.
The record group is open to research.
The Civil Service Study Commission was created on October 14, 1935 by Governor Frank D. Fitzgerald under authority of Public Act 195 of the Public Acts of 1931. The commission, chaired by University of Michigan professor James K. Pollock, was instructed to survey current personnel practices of the state "with a view to determining, in as accurate a way as possible, the most important evils from which the state has been suffering." Under the existing patronage system of government employment, a change in administration usually meant wholesale personnel changes regardless of the competence and merit of the individual then holding any given position. The study commission, in its report, proposed legislation which would correct these shortcomings.
Based upon the recommendations of the commission, the Michigan legislature in 1937 passed a bill designed to correct the evil and inefficiencies of political patrons with the creation of a Civil Service Commission appointed by the governor. This Commission, in turn, would select a personnel director who would prepare the necessary rules and regulations and who would begin the process of classifying each and every state job.
These records, maintained by commission chair James K. Pollock, include administrative files relating to the operation of the commission. There are also materials relating to the survey undertaken by the commission, to the hearings held, and to the drafting of the report prior to its submission to the governor.
Subjects:
Civil service.
Contributors:
Brake, D. Hale, 1891-1979; Bromage, Arthur W. (Arthur Watson), 1904-1979.; Comstock, William Alfred, 1877-1949.; Diggs, Charles C.; Dunckel, Miller Lewis, 1899-; Fitzgerald, Frank Dwight, 1885-1939.; Green, Fred W. (Fred Warren), 1872-1936.; Haber, William, 1899-1988.; Hayden, Joseph Ralston, 1887-1945.; Meader, George, 1907-1994; Murphy, Frank, 1890-1949.; Nichols, Haskell Linton, 1896-; Osborn, Chase S. (Chase Salmon), b. 1860.; Picard, Frank A., 1889-1963.; Pollock, James K. (James Kerr), 1898-1968; Shields, Edmund Claude, 1871-1947.; Vandenberg, Arthur H. (Arthur Hendrick), 1884-1951.; Van Wagoner, Murray Delos, 1898-; White, Leonard Dupee, 1891-1958.
- Commission records
  - Report: Personnel Administration in the State of Michigan (Box 1)
  - General Correspondence
    - A-Z (Box 1)
    - Nichols, Haskell L. (Box 1)
    - Shields, Edmund C. (Box 1)
    - Administrative Board (Box 1)
    - Applications for Positions (Box 1)
    - Lansing Office (Box 1)
    - Merit System Association, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - Public Administration Service. Stone, Belsey, Brownlaw (Box 1)
    - Public Administration Service, Pais, Robinson (Box 1)
    - Public Administration Service, General (Box 1)
    - C.S.S.C. Survey Correspondence with N.Y.A. (Box 1)
    - C.S.S.C. Survey Correspondence with Departments and Institutions, 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Memoranda, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Minutes of Meetings (Box 2)
  - Documentary Record
    - Memos (Box 2)
    - Journals, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Marked Bills (Box 2)
  - S.E.R.A. Administration Committee on Civil Service, 4 folders (Box 2)
  - Merit System Association Documents, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Merit System Association Committee on Popular Propositions, 4 folders (Box 2)
  - Civil Service Conference (Box 2)
  - New Michigan Civil Service System (Box 2)
  - Civil Service on Constitutional Amendment. (Box 2)
  - Committee on Personnel Standards-Interstate Conference of Unemployment Compensation Administrators (Box 2)
  - Full Text of Proposed Civil Service Bill for State's Employees (Box 2)
  - Mounted Clippings 1936-1937 (Box 2)
  - Report of Commission
    - First Draft (Box 3)
    - Proposed Civil Service Bill
      - Second Draft (Box 3)
      - Third Draft (Box 3)
      - Fourth Draft, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - Last Draft, 5 folders (Box 3)
      - Summary; Comments on Bill, 4 folders (Box 3)
      - Final Copy, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - Upson's Copy (Box 3)
      - Printer's Copy, 3 folders (Box 3)
      - Legislative Suggestions, 3 folders (Box 3)
    - Public Relations
      - Clippings, pictures, speeches, etc. (Box 3)
      - News releases March 7, 1936-August 11, 1936 (Box 3)
  - Mailing List and Letters Requesting Reports, 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Original Field Notes, including schedule of departmental progress, 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Study on Turnover (Box 3)
  - Daily reports on Study of Turnover and Salaries, 4 folders (Box 3)
  - Questionnaire Progress Report (Box 3)
  - Hearings
    - Kalamazoo February 1936 (Box 3)
    - Lansing March 1936, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Lansing April 1936 (Box 3)
    - Grand Rapids February 1936, 3 folders (Box 4)
    - Detroit and Escanaba May 1936 (Box 4)
    - Saginaw May, 1936 (Box 4)
  - Questionnaire Stencil of Accompanying Letter. (Box 4)
  - Instructions to Coders (Box 4)
  - Financial Record
    - Invoice Vouchers, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Monthly Statements (Box 4)
    - Purchase Orders (Box 4)
    - Delivery Department Requisitions (Box 4)
    - Traveling Expense Vouchers (Box 4)
  - Salary Rates of Employees Receiving no Maintenance (Box 4)
  - Departmental Payrolls, 3 folders (Box 4)
  - Report of State Highway Department (Box 4)
  - Outline of Personnel Survey of Michigan State Government (Box 4)
  - Lists of State Departments, Institutions, Boards, Commissions (Box 4)
  - Historical File, 4 folders (Box 4)
  - Loose Clippings (Box 5)
  - Loose Clippings (Box 6)
    (continued)